Alexander Giovannelli

Phone: +1-740-258-9709 Email: agiovannelli@vt.edu

Site: https://agiovannelli.github.io/

Summary

My research interest lies in the intersections of Human-Computer Interaction (HCI), Augmented/Virtual Reality (AR/VR), and 3D User Interfaces (3DUI). My current work involves prototyping and evaluating communication methods for collaborative work in AR/VR. Specifically, I am exploring how we could improve non-verbal communicative cues when using avatars and visual information in immersive collaboration applications.

EDUCATION

Virginia Tech

Ph.D. in Computer Science advised by Doug A. Bowman, GPA: 4.00/4.00

Blacksburg, VA, USA

Aug. 2021–Present

University of Cincinnati Cincinnati, OH, USA

B.S. in Computer Engineering with German Studies minor, GPA: 3.30/4.00 Aug. 2013–May 2018

SKILLS

Programming Languages: C#, JavaScript, Java, Python, HTML, CSS

Productivity Tools: Unity, Git, JMP, SPSS, LaTeX, Tableau

EXPERIENCE

Lawrence Livermore National Laboratory

Livermore, CA, USA

Computing Research Intern

Summer 2023

- Perform contextual inquiry and analysis to derive research intent and contribution for project team
- Create prototype applications for virtual reality experiences using C# and Unity technologies
- Facilitate meetings between multi-disciplinary project stakeholders

Virginia Tech

Blacksburg, VA, USA

Graduate Research Assistant

Summer 2022 & Spring 2023

- Conduct research regarding collaboration using avatars in augmented and virtual reality
- Generate prototype applications and experimental studies using C# and Unity technologies
- Design and administer user studies in accordance with Institutional Review Board regulations

JPMorgan Chase & Co.

Columbus, OH, USA

Jul. 2018-Jul. 2021

Associate Software Engineer I

- $-\,$ Developed front-end features for Chase.com using JavaScript, HTML, and CSS technologies
- Designed and implemented minimum viable product user interfaces via Figma design tool
- Authored technical documentation for product owners and developers
- Appointed subject matter expert in behavioral-driven development and CI/CD initiatives

Siemens Healthineers

Forchheim, BY, DE

Jan. 2017–Aug. 2017

Software Engineer Intern

- Developed back-end software for use in advanced therapy devices using the C# programming language
- Created system architecture diagrams to record project design changes and behaviors with Sparx Enterprise Architect
- Represented project team in international software integration meetings using German and English languages

Projects

- Avatars for Multiscale Collaborative Virtual Environments Mar. 2023–Present Design and prototyping of a virtual environment for collaboration in multiscale inspection processes
- Virtual Avatar Reaction Visualizations in VR Jun. 2022-Mar. 2023 Development of a virtual environment for user studies investigating avatar reaction visualizations in collaboration
- Environment for Intermittent Typing Experiments in VR Jan. 2022–May 2022 Creation of a virtual environment with mixed reality capabilities for conducting text-entry user studies

Publications

- A. Giovannelli, F. Rodrigues, S. Davari, I. A. Tahmid, L. Lane, C. Connor, K. Davidson, G. N. Ramirez, B. David-John, and D. A. Bowman, "Clue hog: An immersive competitive lock-unlock experience using hook on go-go technique for authentication in the metaverse", in 2023 IEEE Conference on Virtual Reality and 3D User Interfaces Abstracts and Workshops (VRW), 2023, pp. 945–946.
- J. Thomas, S. W. Lee, A. Giovannelli, L. Lane, and D. Bowman, "A communication-focused framework for understanding immersive collaboration experiences", in 2023 IEEE Conference on Virtual Reality and 3D User Interfaces Abstracts and Workshops (VRW), 2023, pp. 301–304.
- A. Giovannelli, L. Lisle, and D. A. Bowman, "Exploring the impact of visual information on intermittent typing in virtual reality", in 2022 IEEE International Symposium on Mixed and Augmented Reality (ISMAR), 2022, pp. 8–17.
- L. Lisle, F. Lu, S. Davari, I. A. Tahmid, A. Giovannelli, C. Llo, L. Pavanatto, L. Zhang, L. Schlueter, and D. A. Bowman, "Clean the ocean: An immersive vr experience proposing new modifications to go-go and wim techniques", in 2022 IEEE Conference on Virtual Reality and 3D User Interfaces Abstracts and Workshops (VRW), 2022, pp. 920–921.
- E. Mohammadrezaei, A. Giovannelli, L. Lane, and D. Gračanin, "A digital twin based approach to smart lighting design", in 2022 Winter Simulation Conference (WSC), 2022.

Awards & Scholarships

•	Davenport Leadership Fellowship	2023-2024
•	Honorable Mention for Best IEEE ISMAR 2022 Conference Paper [3]	2022
•	Best 3DUI Contest Entry [4]	2022

Teaching

• Graduate Teaching Assistant at Virginia Tech Fall 2022 Comparative Languages (CS-3304)

• Graduate Teaching Assistant at Virginia Tech Fall 2021 & Spring 2022 Software Design & Data Structures (CS-2114)

Organizations

•	Member of Computer Science Graduate Student Council	2021-Present
	Represented the interests of the CS graduate student body and assisted in event planning	
•	Member of the Center for Human-Computer Interaction	2021-Present
	Active participant in the Center seminars regarding the study of human-computer interaction	